<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preach'd before the King in the Cathedral Church of Winchester upon Sunday, Septemb. 9, 1683 being the day of publick thanksgiving for the deliverance of His Sacred Majesties person and government from the late treasonable conspiracy / by F. Turner ...</title>
            <author>Turner, Francis, 1638?-1700.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 59 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63881</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T3282</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1798</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12242375</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12242375</idno>
            <idno type="VID">56821</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63881)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 56821)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 901:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preach'd before the King in the Cathedral Church of Winchester upon Sunday, Septemb. 9, 1683 being the day of publick thanksgiving for the deliverance of His Sacred Majesties person and government from the late treasonable conspiracy / by F. Turner ...</title>
                  <author>Turner, Francis, 1638?-1700.</author>
                  <author>Charles II, King of England, 1630-1685.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Benj. Tooke ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms CXLIV, 9-10 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:56821:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:56821:1"/>
            <p> A SERMON Preach'd before the KING In the Cathedral Church of WINCHESTER, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon</hi> Sunday, <hi>Septemb.</hi> 9. 1683. BEING THE Day of Publick Thankſgiving FOR THE DELIVERANCE OF <hi>His Sacred Majeſties Perſon and Government</hi> From rhe Late Treaſonable CONSPIRACY. BY <hi>F. T<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RNER,</hi> D. D. Dean of <hi>Windſor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="license">
                  <body>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Publiſhed by his Majeſties ſpecial Command.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Benj. Tooke,</hi> at the Ship in S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard. 1683.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:56821:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:56821:2"/>
            <head>A SERMON ON PSAL. cxliv. 9, 10.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I will ſing a new Song unto thee, O God, and ſing Praiſes unto thee upon a ten-ſtringed Lute;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou haſt given Victory unto Kings: and haſt deliver'd</hi> David <hi>thy Servant from the peril of the Sword.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>IF ever any might preſume to take up the words of <hi>David</hi> in another Pſalm where he ſays in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of himſelf and of God's own People, <hi>Like as we have heard ſo have we ſeen in the City of our God, i. e.</hi> in the Church, <hi>God upholdeth the ſame for ever;</hi> We may be allow'd to take them up at this time, and to ſpeak them in our own behalf. If ever thoſe words of his might be apply'd by way of comparing the Great <hi>Deliverances</hi> which Almighty God has afforded to <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Kingdoms</hi> in Ages paſt, with Mercies no leſs wonderful in the preſent Age; Then I may juſtly
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:56821:3"/> apply thoſe words with reference to the words of my Text: I take it out of a Pſalm appointed in part of our <hi>Office</hi> for this <hi>Solemn Thanksgiving;</hi> and there's none but at firſt hearing my Text read may ſee it as it were fulfilled once more in our own Story, and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly accompliſht on this Good Day: for we hear in my Text of <hi>a Victory given by God to a King,</hi> and now we ſee a King who having ſtood as it were in a Battel not for a ſingle day onely, but for ſeveral months, his Enemies are ſo diſappointed, and defeated now, that we may truly ſay, <hi>God has given him</hi> a Noble <hi>Victory:</hi> We hear of a King in my Text, <hi>Deliver'd from the peril of the Sword;</hi> for 'tis plain this Pſalm was written by <hi>David</hi> after he was Eſtabliſht upon his Throne, ſince he ſpeaks to God in the ſecond verſe, <hi>my Deliverer, my Shield, and he in whom I truſt, who ſubdueth my People that is under me.</hi> But we cannot tell whether this Pſalm were written before or after his Encounters with <hi>Abſolom,</hi> the Son of his own Bowels <hi>that ſought his Life,</hi> or with <hi>Sheba</hi> that manag'd a <hi>Riſing</hi> in the City againſt him, till the Loyal Party of the City pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail'd, and the Traitor loſt his Head: therefore I make no reflection upon thoſe paſſages, for tis more than I can prove that <hi>David</hi> himſelf reflected upon them, here. But there's no queſtion he had an Eye to all the Terrible Hazards he had run before he was Crown'd, when Saul <hi>and his bloudy houſe</hi> were <hi>hunting</hi> him <hi>like a Partridge upon the Mountains:</hi> So that not his own Houſe, which ſhould be a Man's Caſtle and his Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary; not his own Bed, which was made to be quiet in;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:56821:3"/> not thoſe very places whither he fled for Refuge, were free <hi>from the peril of the Sword.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This then <hi>we hear</hi> from the Text compar'd with the Story of that King; and (to keep far enough off not only from cold and frivolous Parallels, but alſo from odious Compariſons) I ſhall only ſay, we <hi>ſee a King</hi> preſerved from the ſame Implacable Enemy that has purſu'd him above theſe <hi>Forty Years;</hi> but a much more formidable Enemy ſince he conceal'd his Enmity, than when he declar'd himſelf openly, even by ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a Price upon the Moſt Sacred Head.</p>
            <p>But <hi>David</hi> in all theſe Reflexions either upon his Dangers or his Deliverances, looks up to Heaven, he acknowledges, <hi>that the Race is not to the Swift, nor the Battel to the Strong;</hi> and tho' it be added by <hi>Solomon that Time and Chance happen to all things,</hi> his meaning was, that many things look indeed like Chance, tho guided by a Hand of <hi>Providence,</hi> to moſt unſeen, which yet was moſt viſible to King <hi>David</hi> in the whole Courſe of his Fortunes; therefore he gives the Honor to God alone. He thanks him not only for his own proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Succeſſes, but in behalf of all the <hi>Crowned Heads</hi> in the World, <hi>it is he that giveth Victory unto Kings:</hi> to the ſame Great God of Heaven he aſcribes their Preſervation from ſo many Horrid Conſpiracies, as while there is a <hi>Devil</hi> in Hell, and ſo many of his Agents upon Earth, will never ceaſe to be carryed on; and when they are taken off, <hi>it is He</hi> the King of Kings that <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livers his Servant</hi> David, or by parity of reaſon, any other <hi>Sovereign Prince,</hi> that may be ſtyl'd his <hi>Servant, from the hurtful Sword.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:56821:4"/>
            <p> Laſtly, to compleat the Solemnity and Honorary Part of his <hi>Thanksgivings</hi> upon theſe Accounts, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves to celebrate his Victory and his Deliverance, with ſuch <hi>Muſick</hi> as is proper to be uſed in the <hi>Worſhip</hi> of God, and together with <hi>Church-Muſick</hi> to Introduce its beſt Siſter and Heavenly Twin, <hi>i. e. Divine Poetry,</hi> wherein he will endeavour at Higher and Nobler Strains than ordinary. <hi>I will ſing a new Song unto thee O God: I will ſing Praiſes unto thee upon a ten-ſtringed Lute.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now I cannot deny but many of the modern <hi>Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitors</hi> are careful, in their Deſcants on my Text, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct us that the religious Uſe of Inſtrumental <hi>Muſick</hi> was purely <hi>Moſaical</hi> and <hi>Typical;</hi> that it was adapted to the groſſer and duller Conſtitution of the <hi>Jewiſh Votaries,</hi> but by no means to be taken for our Pattern, nor imitated under the <hi>Goſpel.</hi> But if all this were <hi>Typical,</hi> I would gladly learn what <hi>a Ten-ſtringed Lute</hi> was a <hi>Type</hi> of; I would fain know too, whether the Piety of thoſe <hi>Reformers</hi> be ſo much more Refin'd and Exalted than was that of <hi>David,</hi> that they refuſe and deſpiſe ſuch low <hi>Diſpenſations</hi> as theſe, which he made good uſe of. I would willingly underſtand, why they are not as well pleaſed with good Inſtrumental <hi>Muſick</hi> in ſome few Churches, as they are with ill Vocal Muſick in many Churches. In ſhort, if I find it in uſe with other Nations as old as <hi>Homer</hi>'s time, with Nations who never received the <hi>Law,</hi> and with the <hi>Jews</hi> before they received the <hi>Law</hi> upon Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> (for <hi>Miriam</hi> the Siſter of <hi>Aaron</hi> and the Virgins that bore her Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:56821:4"/> to celebrate their Deliverance out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> played with their <hi>Timbrels</hi> and <hi>danc'd</hi> to the Song of <hi>Moſes)</hi> I muſt conclude it a piece of <hi>Natural Religion,</hi> to which the common Light of Reaſon directs all Civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lized Nations, eſpecially upon any general Jubile and <hi>Publick Thanksgiving;</hi> and if ever any Prince and People had reaſon to ſing <hi>Te Deum,</hi> to raiſe their Affections with Voices, and Strings and Inſtruments of Wind fit for their <hi>Songs of Deliverance</hi> (as <hi>David</hi> calls them) we have reaſon to do it on <hi>This Day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tho this being no common <hi>Day</hi> I muſt be more particular than to ſpend all my time upon any Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-place; yet I have warrant enough to draw from the ſpecial Caſe of <hi>David</hi> towards ſome general Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations; for this Propoſition, <hi>It is God that giveth Victory unto Kings,</hi> is virtually and implicitely uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal; he does not ſay that God always <hi>gives them Victory:</hi> We know it has been given againſt the Beſt of <hi>Kings</hi> to the Worſt of all his <hi>Subjects;</hi> but the meaning is, that whenever a King is a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querour, God <hi>gives him Victory:</hi> Nor does he ſay that Every Sovereign Prince is Conſtantly Deliver'd, as <hi>David</hi> was <hi>from the Peril of the Sword.</hi> Alaſs was our late Royal Martyr <hi>ſo</hi> Delivered from it? In the higheſt and trueſt ſenſe of the word, he was never more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered from all the Evils of this World than when he was delivered up by Gods unſearchable Counſels to the Will of his Enemies; but yet not ſo delivered as <hi>David</hi> with a Temporal Deliverance. This only can be gathered, that whenever theſe Sacred Princes
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:56821:5"/> are ſo delivered as to be preſerved from the Sword, (and ſo they are moſt frequently;) ſo as to be reſcued out of the very Jaws of Death, 'tis by an extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Vigilance of the <hi>Divine Providence</hi> over them, 'tis God is their Guardian, and not Man. <hi>There is no King</hi> (ſays the ſame Royal <hi>Prophet</hi> in another place) <hi>that can be ſaved by the Multitude of an Hoſt; a mighty Man is not delivered by much ſtrength. i. e.</hi> 'tis not the Number of his Forces that can ſecure the greateſt Prince, nor the Courage and Power of the moſt Giant-like man, no, tho' he has never ſo numerous a Party on his ſide, that can Preſerve or Suſtain him. And as no King is to put his Truſt in the Number or the Fortitude of his People, ſo neither is any People to Confide in the Wiſdome of their Heads, or in the vaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their Body, to oppoſe their Lawful Prince; for it follows, <hi>the Lord bringeth the Counſel of the Heathen to nought, He maketh the Devices of the People of none effect.</hi> Now in the Book of <hi>Pſalms</hi> the <hi>Heathen</hi> do commonly ſignifie the <hi>Godleſs-men:</hi> So 'tis as if he had ſaid, <hi>whatſoever</hi> Godleſs men deſign or propoſe to themſelves contrary to the Will of God, he blaſts and fruſtrates their Plots, he diſſipates all their Cabals, he unravels all their Intrigues, be they never ſo cunningly manag'd by ſuch as have erected themſelves into Secret Councils, be they never ſo ſtrongly backt by <hi>Factious Aſſociations;</hi> ſtill God does in his good time make it appear, that he governs the World, he makes them feel his hand that think to wreſt the Scepter from them that hold it for him. Whoever they are that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:56821:5"/> uſe indirect and unlawful means to Raiſe or Eſtabliſh, or but to Secure themſelves, to ſet up as it were for themſelves, <hi>without God in the World;</hi> they take the certain courſe either to miſcarry with their Deſign, or if they do gain their Point, yet their Succeſs it ſelf is a judgment upon them: proportionable to the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their Sin will be their Puniſhment; which if it comes in this world, is commonly fetch'd out of the very bowels of the Sin that deſerv'd it, and ſo as the Hand of God is illuſtriouſly viſible in it.</p>
            <p>But to be more diſtinct, I ſhall lay the main deſign of my Text into theſe three Heads of my Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I take the firſt of them from the very words of <hi>David, That ſince it is God who giveth Victory unto Kings, it is better to truſt in the Lord, than to put any confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, <hi>That ſuch as will not truſt in God as a Deliverer from any Dangers they fear, but will take the Sword againſt their Lawful Prince upon any Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence whatſoever; their Sentence is read in the words of our Bleſſed Saviour;</hi> They that take the Sword ſhall Periſh by the Sword.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly, <hi>That there is a Peculiar hand of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence over Kings and Princes to deliver them from the hurtful Sword; and ſo alſo over all their Loyal Subjects and Good People, that will but truſt God and walk in his holy ways.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:56821:6"/>
            <p> Firſt then, <hi>Since it is God who giveth Victory unto Kings, it is better to truſt in the Lord, than to put any Confidence in man.</hi> What need I look any farther for Proof of ſo plain a thing than to this Great Man in the Text?</p>
            <p>When he yielded to that great Temptation <hi>of Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring the People,</hi> an Act which God interpreted to be <hi>relying on the Arm of Fleſh,</hi> and priding himſelf in the many that he had at his Service, inſtead of depending upon God, then God was pleas'd immediately to ſhew Himſelf; the vaſt Muſter-Roll of his Fighting men was quickly diminiſh'd by an Epidemical Plague, a Judgment worthy of God; a fair warning for every Great Man that puts his truſt in the Multitude, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially for him that <hi>follows a Multitude to do Evil,</hi> tho' he vainly ſuppoſes that Good may come of it, or at leaſt that a great Evil and Miſchief cannot be avoided but by running along with the ſtream. This Principle of yielding, and ſteering a crooked Courſe for fear of the Torrent, was by a Noble <hi>Engliſh</hi> Martyr within the memory of man, moſt Chriſtianly Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt and Condemn'd with his laſt breath, as that which had brought upon him the Guilt of Innocent Blood<note place="margin">Ld. <hi>Capel.</hi>
               </note>. In ſuch hard Caſes as theſe, the reſolution of <hi>David</hi> (tho' ſomewhat of the lateſt for him after he had <hi>Numbred the People)</hi> ſhould be our Rule, <hi>Let us now fall into hands of the Lord, for his mercies are great, and let us not fall into the hands of men:</hi> Then how low ſoever we may fall we are ſure to fall decently, with an humble great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:56821:6"/> and with the honeſt Pride of a good Conſcience; nay then we have reaſon to be conſident, that <hi>God is on our right hand, therefore we ſhall not fall, by thoſe floods of Belial;</hi> or, <hi>thoſe overflowings of ungodly men, which made even</hi> David <hi>afraid;</hi> for God takes to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf this Glory, <hi>that He ſtills the raging of the Sea,</hi> and <hi>the noiſe of its Waves, and the madneſs of the People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if ever any one thought to carry all before him by the <hi>Number</hi> and Force of his Armed men, in ſpight of the Living God, it was <hi>Senacherib;</hi> The Speech that was ſpoken in his Name by <hi>Rabſhekah</hi> to the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple on the Wall, was like that of the Gyant <hi>Capaneus,</hi> whom the <hi>Poet</hi> repreſents upon the Walls of <hi>Thebes</hi> daring and defying all the Gods of Heaven and of Earth. But when the Tumor of the <hi>Aſſyrians Pride</hi> was lanc'd by an <hi>Angel</hi>'s Sword, (which in one Night cut off a hundred fourſcore and five thouſand of his fighting men; and ſo gave a great Victory to the King of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and ſo delivered <hi>Hezekiah</hi> the Son of <hi>David, from the hurtful Sword)</hi> then does not <hi>Senacherib</hi> bluſh by falling low on his Face to a God of wood or of ſtone to give himſelf the Lie; he that confeſs'd no other God than his own ſtrong Arm (to that alone he gives the Attribute of Omnipotence) he is found upon his Knees to his God <hi>Niſroch;</hi> he who not only deſpiſed the Servants and Worſhippers of the God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but in compariſon of his own ſtrength, derided the Power of a Deity, and prickt all his Religion upon the end of his Sword, this Scorner
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:56821:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> of God is ſlain by two of of his own Sons while he was crouching to a thing without Senſe or Life; in the very Act of his Publick Adoration, God in his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Wiſdome ordering it ſo, that he ſhould ſeal his Faith (ſuch a faith as it was) with his own Blood, that not only his Crime and his Puniſhment; but his Recantation too might be publiſh'd to all the World.</p>
            <p>But ſure I may take your Aſſent to this for granted, that <hi>'tis better to truſt in God than to put any Confidence in Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. I proceed in the ſecond place to ſhew more largely, <hi>That ſuch as will not truſt in God as a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverer from any dangers they fear, but will take the Sword againſt their Lawful Prince, upon any pretence whatſoever, their Sentence is read in the words of our bleſſed Saviour,</hi> They that take the Sword ſhall periſh with the Sword.</p>
            <p>This alſo will beſt appear by ſome clear and proper Examples, even <hi>David</hi> the Hero in my Text, He who had ſhew'd himſelf infinitly tender of <hi>touching the Lords Anointed,</hi> tho' himſelf were the next to ſucceed, when he made but one falſe Step in point of Duty to his King and Love to his Country, it coſt him almoſt as dear as his very Life; for when King <hi>Saul</hi> had driven him from his Country, when being purſu'd and perſecuted to extremity, he did but fly for refuge to the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtins,</hi> thoſe mortal Enemies of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> how quickly do they <hi>call his ſins to remembrance? Is this not</hi> David <hi>of whom they ſang one to another,</hi> Saul <hi>hath ſlain his Thouſands and</hi> David <hi>his Ten Thouſands?</hi> Then was
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:56821:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> he fain wiſely to act the fool, and to counterfeit <hi>the Mad-man,</hi> to let <hi>his ſpittle fall down upon his Beard.</hi> Yet was not that ſo abject or ſo ridiculous a ſpectacle as to ſee one lick the ſpittle of the people from the very Ground, as the greateſt man muſt do that would court a Party, and ſet up for baſe Populari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: He muſt be contented not onely to play the fool for Company, and to cant with them; but he muſt play the Bedlam too, or elſe he muſt leave his Party. Well under this Diſguiſe of a man that had loſt his wits, and was not worth their looking after, <hi>David</hi> eſcapes from that fatal Court to a Cave; He raiſes ſome forces: nor was he to blame for this, to go about with a Guard, when his Life was unjuſtly attempted by the <hi>Philiſtins,</hi> the common Enemy. <hi>Every one</hi> (we are told) <hi>that was in debt, and every one that was diſcontented gather'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves unto him; Multi quibus <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tile Bellum,</hi> many to whom War and Troubles would afford a ſubſiſtance: now he thought himſelf conſiderable enough with his flying Army to offer his ſervice again to the ſame King <hi>Achiſh</hi> of <hi>Gath;</hi> and perſonating the Lunatick no more, he is kindly receiv'd there. And yet 'tis plain he never intended to make War on their Side againſt his own Prince and People, for while he dwelt among them he diverted and imployed his Forces another way againſt ſome of the Borderers, the Old Enemies of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> But then to what cruel hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips was he reduced, even to put all to the Sword, that none might ſurvive to tell any Tales of him?
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:56821:8"/> What pitiful Evaſions; what officious Equivocations was he driven upon, to make the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> believe that he was heartily theirs? and then does King <hi>Achiſh</hi> bring him to the Teſt, to fight with <hi>Iſrael? And</hi> Achiſh <hi>ſaid unto</hi> David, <hi>Know thou aſſuredly that thou ſhalt go out with me to Battel, thou and thy men.</hi> There's no ſtepping back for a man once en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gag'd on the wrong ſide, he muſt either go through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out with his new Friends, or quit them in plain Field. He anſwers the Prince whom he had made his Maſter, in general terms, <hi>Surely thou ſhalt know what thy Servant can do.</hi> He and his men keep <hi>in the Rear</hi> on the Day of Battel; what he meant to do, or which way he deſign'd to extricate him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf out of theſe Difficulties into which his falſe Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks had caſt him, 'tis impoſſible for us to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine. Perhaps he would have thrown himſelf and his Forces between the two Armies, to prevent the Fight and to mediate a Peace, and ſo he would have ſatisfied both his Obligations, the one of Loyalty to his Prince, the other of Gratitude to his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector.</p>
            <p>But the Providence of God decided the Caſe and drew him out of the Snare, but made him take ſhame upon him, when <hi>the Princes of the</hi> Philiſtines urg'd their King to ſend him away in diſgrace, <hi>Make this fellow return, and let him not go down with us to Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel, leſt in the Battel he be an Adverſary to us, for where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with ſhould he reconcile himſelf to his Maſter, ſhould it not be with the Heads of theſe men?</hi> Thus they in a
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:56821:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> manner caſhier'd him, as one to be juſtly ſuſpected for a double Traitor; and though they cenſur'd him unjuſtly, yet the whole Story may ſerve to ſtrengthen my Concluſion; which <hi>David</hi> had often experimented to be moſt true; that <hi>as an humble Confidence of Gods Protection over us, if we reſolve to live in his moſt holy fear, is the moſt infallible courſe we can take to continue in ſafety, ſo on the other ſide all Policy that ſwerves from the ſtrict Rule of Conſcience, does rather procure than prevent extream Danger.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to confirm this obſervation from Experience older than <hi>David</hi> and yet ſtill to keep within the Sacred ſtory. The <hi>Men of</hi> Iſrael <hi>ſaid unto</hi> Gideon (that was in the time of the Judges) <hi>Rule thou over us, both thou and thy Son and thy Sons Son alſo.</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God had choſen him before to be their Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Chief; but what they offer him now was more than an <hi>Act of Recognition,</hi> or an Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment of his Right; for by this Act they bind themſelves and their Poſterity to be ſubject to him and his. But how did they keep their Faith with him? Much at the ſame rate as the unconſtant Multitude is wont to keep it. As ſoon as <hi>Gideon</hi> was dead, Abimelech <hi>his Son by a Concubine</hi> (as he is ſtil'd) inſinuates himſelf into them; They <hi>furniſh him with money</hi> under hand, wherewith <hi>he hires vain and light Perſons</hi> to follow him; for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ſuch are the Followers of <hi>Mock-Princes:</hi> with the help of this Noble Retinue he aſſaſſinates all
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:56821:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> the <hi>ſeventy</hi> legitimate <hi>Sons</hi> of his Father <hi>upon one</hi> ſtone; yet the People have ſtill that wicked Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality for him as <hi>to make him their King;</hi> But how did this Murderous Traitor and his Abettors proſper? <hi>Jotham</hi> the Youngeſt Son of <hi>Gideon</hi> and the only Son that ſurviv'd the <hi>Maſſacre,</hi> cryes as a Prophet from God againſt the Uſurper; and denounces <hi>that fire ſhall come out of the Bramble</hi> (ſo in his Parable he calls that Baſe Son) and that <hi>this fire ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour their Cedars of Lebanon,</hi> their Noble men that rais'd him. And preſently after that, we ſhall find that their Underwoods, <hi>i. e.</hi> the Common People were deſtroyed in the flame of their own blowing up. For the next account we receive is, that <hi>God ſent an Evil Spirit between</hi> Abimelech <hi>and the men of</hi> Sichem: He ſent <hi>i. e.</hi> he ſuffer'd the <hi>Devil</hi> as his Inſtrument of Vengeance to go, and he gave him power over them: And now they grow as weary of their Pageant as once they were fond of it; they hold their <hi>Cloſe Meetings</hi> againſt him, 'tis ſaid <hi>they met in the Houſe of their God to Eat and Drink, and to Curſe</hi> Abimelech; this was to turn their Church into a True <hi>Conventicle,</hi> where they carryed on the work of the day in their two laudable Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes, whereof one was inveighing againſt the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, though it was of their own ſetting up; and the other was indulging their ſenſual Appetites under the Cloak of Religion. Then we are told, <hi>the men of</hi> Sichem <hi>dealt Treacherouſly with</hi> Abimelech, as thoſe that have once been fellow-Traitors to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:56821:9"/> their Lawful Governours do ſeldome long continue faithful to one another. What Tumults there follow'd? What Inſurrections? How the Fields were dyed with gore, and how much Blood ran down the Streets of their City, you may read in that noble Story; which finiſhes at laſt in the moſt ignominious Death of that mighty <hi>Man, who took not God for his ſtrength,</hi> he <hi>periſhes by the hand of a Woman.</hi> To make it the more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable; he that had murder'd <hi>ſeventy of his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren upon one ſtone,</hi> has his own Brains daſh'd out by another <hi>ſtone:</hi> and to ſhew that the hand of God was in all this, we are told expreſly, <hi>And all the Evil of the Men of</hi> Sichem <hi>did God render upon their own heads, and upon them came the Curſe of</hi> Jotham.</p>
            <p>But becauſe this diſtruſting of God and (inſtead of doing that which <hi>David</hi> preſſes ſo paſſionately, <hi>O tarry thou the Lords leiſure)</hi> being ready to ſay with that impious Noble-man that was at laſt trodden to Death by the People, <hi>Why tarry we for the Lord any longer?</hi> Becauſe this fatal Impatience ſeems to be now one of our <hi>National Sins,</hi> I ſhall urge againſt the ſad effects of it ſome ſuch Examples as ſhall be <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional</hi> and Virtually a Multitude of Examples; <hi>Zede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah</hi> the King of <hi>Judah</hi> having abſolutely ſubmitted to the great King of <hi>Babylon,</hi> 'tis ſaid he <hi>Rebelled againſt King</hi> Nebuchadnezzar, <hi>who had made him ſwear by God:</hi> Therefore by the way, the reſiſting a <hi>Lawful Prince</hi> to whom an Oath of Obedience has once been taken, tho' he be a <hi>Heathen Prince,</hi> as <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> was, is no better than a downright Perjury, and a wicked
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:56821:10"/> Rebellion. So <hi>Jeremiah</hi> the poor deſpis'd <hi>Prophet</hi> of God implies it to be throughout his Prophecy. But what if theſe men were perjur'd Rebels? yet this was always their Note concerning themſelves, <hi>The Temple of the Lord, the Temple of the Lord are theſe, i. e.</hi> they were <hi>the Godly,</hi> they were <hi>the Saints;</hi> juſt as <hi>the True Proteſtant, the True Proteſtant,</hi> is now the Common Cry of thoſe who think that Title a good Apology, and a ſufficient Plea to legitimate Perjury and Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, nay more, he is ſure to be called a Factor for <hi>Babylon</hi> (as <hi>Jeremiah</hi> was call'd) that dares but call it Perjury and Rebellion. But by whatever Names they are pleas'd to call us, I muſt tell them by the way, ſince in Oppoſition to <hi>their Rebellion</hi> we have held our Lives ſo long at the mercy of <hi>their Perjury,</hi> and yet they have found to their Coſt that we have ſtood our ground ſtill in the <hi>Church of</hi> England; they that have try'd us at this rate have given a ſufficient proof that we are ready to lay down our Lives for the <hi>Church of</hi> England. We can ſay no more than this, and we ought to ſay no leſs. But to return from this ſhort occaſional digreſſion to the Story of that Rebellion I was relating; What came of it? That eaſie miſguided Prince <hi>Zedekiah</hi> was utterly loſt, his very Eyes were not left him but only ſo long as to ſee his Sons put to the Sword; the <hi>Temple</hi> that was their <hi>Glory,</hi> and which they turn'd into their <hi>Vain Glory,</hi> was burnt by <hi>Nebuzaradun</hi> the <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> General, the main Body of the People was carryed away <hi>Captive</hi> into that ſame <hi>Babylon,</hi> that Heatheniſh Countrey which they ſo juſtly abhorr'd.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:56821:10"/>
            <p> Again, the ſame turbulent and reſtleſs People being after many Ages in ſome degree re-eſtabliſht by the Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of the <hi>Maccabees,</hi> had made an intire and neceſſary ſurrender of themſelves to the <hi>Romans</hi> as to their Lords and Maſters. Fo fear of giving Umbrage to the <hi>Romans</hi> of any other Pretender to the Crown but <hi>Caeſar,</hi> their carſed Politician <hi>Caiaphas</hi> was for putting our <hi>Bleſſed Lord</hi> to death: thoſe two words <hi>Venient Romani, the</hi> Romans <hi>will come and take away both our Place and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> were effectual incentives to ſtir up the People to Cry, <hi>Crucify him, Crucify him:</hi> As now to Cry loud enough <hi>Popery will come in and ſwallow us up,</hi> ſerves all the turns of any great Incendiary to break through all Human and Divine Laws. But how were thoſe <hi>Phariſees</hi> and <hi>Sadduces,</hi> thoſe Hypocrites and Atheiſts deſtroyed by themſelves? their ſhedding innocent blood (and it was the Blood of God) brought upon them a deluge of blood; at laſt their open Rebellion againſt the <hi>Romans,</hi> their lawful Governours at that time, cauſed their whole Nation to be pluck'd up by the very roots, and to make the Judgment more apparent, when <hi>Titus</hi> the <hi>Roman</hi> came and burnt their <hi>Temple</hi> again, ſo many Ages after its firſt Deſtruction, that ſecond Deſolation came upon them (ſays <hi>Joſephus</hi> their great Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian)<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joſp. de Bell. Jud.</hi> l. 7. c. 9.</note> in the <hi>ſame Month,</hi> on the <hi>ſame day</hi> of the Month that the former fell upon; and when by the ſame <hi>diviſion of Prieſts and Levites,</hi> the <hi>ſame Divine Service</hi> was reading in courſe; <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>Pſalm,</hi> which was written in Admiration of Gods vindictive Juſtice, <hi>O God, to whom Vengeance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth,</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:56821:11"/> 
               <hi>thou God to whom Vengeance belongeth ſhew thy ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. After ſuch inſtances as theſe, I ſhall need no more: and in hopes I have gain'd this ſecond Point, that ſuch as will needs <hi>take the ſword againſt their law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Prince ſhall periſh with the ſword,</hi> I make haſt to my Third and Laſt Part, <hi>That there is a peculiar hand of providence over Kings and Princes; to deliver them from the hurtful Sword: ſo alſo over all their Loyall Subjects and Good People that will but truſt God and walk in his Holy ways.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now then let us look back on the other ſide, and ſee but how well they fard in thoſe ſame great Conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures and Revolutions who took the Prophets Advice <hi>to ceaſe from man,</hi> i. e. <hi>to truſt in God:</hi> Upon how eaſie terms was the whole Nation offered by God to be preſerv'd? He does as it were renew his old promiſe, to <hi>fight for them while they ſhould hold their peace,</hi> if they would but reform their Lives: <hi>thus ſaith the Lord amend our ways and your doings, and I will cauſe you to dwell in this place.</hi> See how God takes to himſelf the Ordering of State-affairs, as the firſt Mover and Manager of all ſecond Cauſes, <hi>then I will cauſe you to dwell in the Land that I gave to your Fathers.</hi> But the greater number of that People would not take God's word, and he dealt with them accordingly: But how was the patient and the peaceful temper of mind ſignally rewarded in the Preſervation of <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> and the Remnant his little Party? how was ſubmiſſion and obedience to their Chief (tho he were dead and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:56821:11"/> gone) nobly requited to <hi>Jeremiahs</hi> beloved <hi>Rechabites</hi> in that very time of the Siege? becauſe they kept to thoſe Conſtitutions which they had received from their Anceſtor, they had a gracious and a glorious promiſe from God, Jonadab <hi>the Son of</hi> Rechab <hi>ſhall not want a man to ſtand before me for ever.</hi> Under what part of Heaven ſoever they have liv'd, I believe God, that this Religious Family was preſerved (when the whole Nation was almoſt extinguiſh'd) to laſt the outmoſt date of this moſt true Promiſe. And if any faith may be given to a <hi>Jewiſh Author,</hi> who Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail'd over the greateſt part of the habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table World, to viſit the diſperſed of his own Nation<note place="margin">Benj. Tudel.</note>; he aſſures us in his <hi>Itinerary,</hi> that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever becomes of his Country-men the Sons of <hi>Abraham,</hi> yet the Poſterity of <hi>Rechab</hi> do ſtill ſubſiſt; that they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy a fair Territory; that they have built a ſtrong City, (which they were not for bidden to do for their neceſſary defence) and are very formidable Neighbours to other petty States among the <hi>Arabs</hi> at this day. Juſt ſo it fell out again at the ſecond deſtruction of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> when the <hi>Romans</hi> took it; <hi>Gallus</hi> began the Siege, but rais'd it again without any reaſon imaginable, except this account may be given of it, that he was over-rul'd from above, to open a paſſage for the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> (who in thoſe days <hi>follow'd nothing but Peace and Holineſs)</hi> to <hi>fly to the Mountains;</hi> ſo that when <hi>Titus</hi> came a few months after to renew the Siege, there was not one <hi>Chriſtian</hi> left in <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Euſeb.</hi> l. 3. c. 5.</note> We muſt needs believe the moſt <hi>Auihentick</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:56821:12"/> Writers of that Story, that the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> all eſcap'd to <hi>Pella,</hi> a City beyond <hi>Jordan,</hi> while the <hi>ſeditious Jews</hi> were not only cut off by the <hi>Romans,</hi> but were all the while killing and ſlaying, and damning one another.</p>
            <p>Take but one inſtance more of God's extraordinary Care of thoſe that will but give credence to his Word, and keep themſelves within any tolerable compaſs of doing their duty; but it ſhall be an inſtance reaching from the beginning to the laſt fatal End of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Government; for during all that time Almighty God was pleas'd to work more than an Anniverſary Miracle for their ſakes, when the Tribes of <hi>Iſrael</hi> went up to their great Solemnities thrice in the Year, leaving their whole Country naked and in a manner expoſed to a Forein Invaſion, God viſibly and gloriouſly perform'd what he had engaged to do for their Security; for he ſtruck their Neighbour-Nations and Powerful Cities that were at Enmity with them, with <hi>Panic Fears,</hi> and the <hi>Terror of the Lord was upon them,</hi> that they druſt make no Inroads on the Holy Land, however abandon'd for the Time by moſt of its own Inhabitants: According to that aſſurance given 'em in that wonderful place of Scripture, <hi>Exodus,</hi> xxxiv. 24. <hi>For I will caſt out the Nations before thee and inlarge thy borders: neither ſhall any man deſire thy Land when thou goeſt up to appear before the Lord thy God thrice in the Year.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if ſuch and ſo extraordinary has been the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence</hi> of God in the preſervation of the obedient People; much more remarkable has the Divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection been over the <hi>Sacred</hi> Perſons of Kings and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:56821:12"/> Princes. I have not time to expatiate on ſo noble a Theam, I will come preſently home to the wonderful Inſtance now before us, and to the peculiar buſineſs of this Day: How was our Native Country, this fruitful Soil, like to have been ſtain'd with a moſt barbarous Aſſaſſination of our Sovereign Lord the King and his Royal Brother, had not their Lives been precious in the ſight of God! There had an Acre of Ground been made an <hi>Aceldama,</hi> a Field of Blood, and conſider pray, you that have in your minds the ſituation of the place where this moſt horrible <hi>Treaſon</hi> ſhould have been acted; was there ever a place more cunningly found out for the Execution of ſo damnable a Deſign? an Incloſure, an errand Pound; in the midſt of it a Houſe as convenient for the reception of all the <hi>Conſpirators</hi> as the Maſter of that Houſe was proper to make One at the head of that execrable Crew. Set then before your Eyes thoſe la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable Images, (but moſt neceſſary to make us ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of our great deliverance) a number of murderous <hi>Phanaticks</hi> in whoſe ſight <hi>Blood was as nothing,</hi> and <hi>Royal</hi> Blood no more to them than the meaneſt, nay the more meritorious Sacrifice; ſuppoſe thoſe Armed Traitors ruſhing out of their lurking-place, while our <hi>Fearleſs Princes</hi> had been talking of indifferent things, or while they had been repoſing themſelves in their Journey, pent up in a Coach, diſabled even from drawing their Swords, or <hi>Dying Nobly;</hi> and for a few of their Guards what could they have done? Alaſs the Blow would have been given before they could have apprehended their Maſter to be in danger. This was a perfect <hi>Powder-Plot</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:56821:13"/> in the moſt <hi>literal ſence,</hi> the deed had been done before the noiſe had been heard, the greateſt Courage upon Earth had been uſeleſs there; in an inſtant the Furies had gain'd their helliſh point, had not Heaven been watchful over us.</p>
            <p>If ever you hear Gods <hi>Providence</hi> call'd in queſtion by our bold <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> choak them with the <hi>fire at New-Market,</hi> which haſtning the King away, ſpoil'd the whole Train that was laid, and by the loſs of a few Houſes pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented three great Kingdoms from periſhing together in one Flame. For can you believe or imagin that all would have ended in a <hi>Maſſacre</hi> of the <hi>Royal</hi> Family? No, doubt you not, the <hi>Maſſacre</hi> would have been carryed on as far as they could againſt all the Royal Party. What elſe could they intend? what other thing could they wiſh? what other cauſe of acting ſo deteſtable a Treaſon? for to take off a moſt merciful King, and his next Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor, who next to him has ſhewed himſelf of a moſt reconcileable Temper; to do all this with a purpoſe of calling in the <hi>next of Kin</hi> to the Crown, who was bound in honour and conſcience to take vengeance upon them; or with a purpoſe of ſetting up ſome other ſingle Perſon that had <hi>no Right;</hi> this is a degree of madneſs which none of theſe ſhrewd <hi>Phanaticks</hi> have to plead in their own excuſe. <hi>Bring forth the Blind that have Eyes, and the deaf that have Ears</hi> (as <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſpeaks) If any man will not ſee a thing ſo clear as this, or if any one will not hear this certain truth, That this Conſpiracy was the goodly fruit of that <hi>Worthy Aſſociation;</hi> the deſign of which was to eſtabliſh their <hi>Common-Wealth</hi> in
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:56821:13"/> the State, and to introduce a <hi>Chaos</hi> or deform'd maſs of all Religions under the falſe Pretence and counterfeit Title of <hi>One Proteſtant Religion in the Church.</hi> But then to bring this to paſs, tho' God only knows what they could have effected, yet they muſt needs have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to cut off immediately all men of note that had adher'd to the Crown, all that had been true to the Church, all that had behav'd themſelves honeſtly in the laſt perplext Five years: Ye had all been <hi>Popiſhly Affected</hi> at leaſt, and the <hi>Proteſtant Flails</hi> (as they call 'em) had flown about your Ears long ago. My thoughts are loſt and <hi>drown'd</hi> in the horrour of what would have follow'd; I may be allowed to uſe that Metaphor of <hi>Drowning,</hi> for <hi>David</hi> uſes it here, praying Almighty <hi>God to ſave him and deliver him out of the great waters, from the hand of ſtrange Children;</hi> for a <hi>Popular Inſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection</hi> is like an <hi>inundation</hi> in the Night, when the Sea beats down its walls: A <hi>Tyrant</hi> makes indeed a horrible noiſe like <hi>Thunder,</hi> but he, like that, does ſeldome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy any great numbers; but an <hi>Enthuſiaſtick Multitude</hi> breaking looſe, do's, like the raging waves, make no diſtinction or ſtop, it bears down all impetuouſly that ſtands before it. I ſpeak not only with regard to thoſe Loyal <hi>Noblemen</hi> and principal <hi>Miniſters of State,</hi> and <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> of the great City, that were marked out and condemn'd to have fallen with the King, and a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular <hi>Butcher</hi> provided for each one of them, But I muſt ſay it to all the worthy Patriots in this Great Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, they ought to make a preſent of their Lives and give them back again to the Service of God <hi>(whoſe</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:56821:14"/> 
               <hi>Service is perfect Freedome)</hi> for perhaps there is not a man among them but owes his Life to the Goodneſs of God in this diſcovery; for what did not thoſe <hi>Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians</hi> ſwallow in their own thoughts? Whoſe Blood did not thoſe <hi>Cannibals</hi> thirſt after? Upon whoſe Eſtate and Fortunes had they not fixt their envious and impudent Eyes? As great a ſhame as it is for ſome profligate and deſperate Wretches to have been left out of the Caballs that manag'd this Conſpiracy, meerly becauſe they knew them to be made up of ſo much Treachery and Falſeneſs, they would not be true, no not to themſelves; <hi>So</hi> great a Shame would it have been for any <hi>Worthy Men</hi> not to have been in their Liſt of <hi>Men worthy;</hi> It would have been a Scandal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed for any man of Honour and of Conſcience to have been ſuffer'd to Live by them, to have ſurviv'd the <hi>Royal Family,</hi> and ſo many good Subjects as would have fallen with it, had the Villains prevail'd.</p>
            <p>And yet perhaps they would have ſpar'd the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying</hi> men as not worth their Anger, ſuch men as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to thrive under all Governments, or can at leaſt be well content to ſit ſtill, indifferent and unconcern'd whatever Religion is uppermoſt in the Church: they are <hi>Animals incombuſtible for Religion,</hi> (as one defines them) and whatever Intereſt prevails in the State, they laugh at the Notion of being <hi>State-Martyrs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I wiſh this ſort of men who pleaſe themſelves with being ſo <hi>Paſſive</hi> in ſo <hi>Active</hi> times as theſe, would conſider what kind of Cenſure or Sentence rather, an Heathen Legiſlator has paſt upon them; <hi>Amongſt</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:56821:14"/> 
               <hi>the Laws of</hi> S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lon (ſays <hi>Plutarch,</hi> the writer of his Life) <hi>that is very peculiar and ſurpriſing, which makes all thoſe Infamous, who ſtand Neuters in a Sedition: for it ſeems he would not have any one Inſenſible and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardleſs of the Publick, and ſecuring his private affairs glory that he had no feeling of the Diſtempers of his Country, but preſently joyn with thoſe that had the Right upon their ſide, aſſiſt and venture with them rather than ſhift out of harms-way, and watch who would get the better.</hi> Theſe are the words of that wiſe man, ſtating and declaring the concern that every Private man ought to ſhew when his Prince or his Country are in danger.</p>
            <p>But now for any of thoſe that are in a publick truſt or have a more ſpecial obligation to be upon the watch for the ſafety of the King and Kingdom; if ſuch men are <hi>aſleep David</hi> being yet a ſubject, tell's them plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>as the Lord liveth</hi> (ſays he) <hi>ye are worthy to die, becauſe ye have not kept your maſter the Lords Anointed. Awake</hi> then you that together <hi>with the land which the Lord gave to your Fathers,</hi> inherit their vertue too, the old Engliſh Loyalty and Courage: lay out your thoughts upon ſomthing more worthy of your ſelves than are thoughts only of your own ſecurity: let every one in his Station do his duty fearleſsly: And they that do ſo prove for the moſt part the wiſeſt as well as the moſt conſcientious, the ſafeſt as well as the nobleſt and beſt <hi>Patriots;</hi> let us ſet it down to our ſelves that <hi>Honeſty is the true Policy,</hi> and let none make that accurſed Converſion of the Propoſition, <hi>as if Policy were the true Honeſty;</hi> unleſs they mean
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:56821:15"/> to revive that old abominable <hi>Gnoſtick</hi> Principle of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance with any <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpations,</hi> or Impoſitions, for fear of Suffering, for fear of that which a Chriſtian would rather wiſh for his own ſake, could it be without other mens guilt, <hi>i. e.</hi> the Crown of <hi>Martyrdom; Ita te alius ſenem cum Petro cingat,</hi> That was St. <hi>Hierom</hi>'s good wiſh to <hi>Damaſus</hi> then Biſhop of <hi>Rome, So let another hind thee when thou art old, as St.</hi> Peter <hi>was bound,</hi> that was, to be carryed to Martyrdom. This would ſeem but a courſe Complement, a piece of ill Courtſhip now, <hi>A wiſh</hi> (ſays <hi>Eraſmus) if any now ſhould make it in behalf of his Holineſs and preſent it in an Epiſtle to him, I wonder</hi> (ſays he) <hi>what Reward he would aſſign him?</hi> Crucem opinor. But let the worſt come to the worſt (as they ſay) if this be the worſt, that it ſhall pleaſe Chriſt to call any of us as the <hi>Angel</hi> from Heaven call'd <hi>St.</hi> John <hi>the Apoſtle, come up hither,</hi> ſhall it be enough to deter us from going thither, that firſt he may happen to call us as he did St. <hi>Peter, Follow me,</hi> that is through death? What a noble <hi>Army of Martyrs</hi> have followed the great <hi>Captain of our Salvation?</hi> The Church the Field of God has been manured, and enriched with the nobleſt compoſt in the World, the Blood of Martyrs; The times and ſeaſons of the Year are bounded out and ſignaliz'd by the <hi>dying Days</hi> of Martyrs: The Chriſtian Temples are dedicated to the <hi>Memorials</hi> of the Martyrs, and Miracles were undeniably wrought at the <hi>Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> of the Bleſſed Martyrs. After all this, men of ſoft and ſmooth inſinuations would introduce a Principle of Self-Preſervation (as they call it) as if it were <hi>unworthy,</hi> as
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:56821:15"/> if it were <hi>unlawful</hi> to ſuffer any thing like Martyrdom, nay as if it were more Chriſtian to be <hi>Rebels</hi> and <hi>Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cides,</hi> than be ſo much as Confeſſors in the Cauſe of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But we that have been ſaved from the <hi>Maſſacre,</hi> we that have received a great and new Mercy our ſelves in this laſt wonderful <hi>Deliverance</hi> of the King from the <hi>hands of his Enemies;</hi> have we not reaſon <hi>to ſing a new Song unto God,</hi> to <hi>ſing praiſes unto him?</hi> And I make no doubt but many of thoſe his Enemies will now change their note, and let them <hi>ſing our new Song,</hi> and <hi>let it come from the ground of the Heart,</hi> as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Give thanks, O</hi> Iſrael, <hi>to God the Lord in the Congregation, from the ground of the heart,</hi> let them joyn with us here in the <hi>Offices</hi> of the Church to bleſs Almighty God for this Day, and for this happy Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very; Upon theſe terms they are welcome not only to <hi>our Communion,</hi> but to that of the <hi>Angels</hi> in Heaven; <hi>for there is joy in the preſence of the Angels of God over one Sinner that Repenteth,</hi> then much more joy over many Repenting Sinners. But then I muſt preſs them vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mently <hi>to bring forth fruits worthy of Repentance.</hi> What Love; what Duty do they owe to God and the King, out of pure gratitude for being afforded as great a delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance as ours, a deliverance from themſelves, from the Plague of their own hearts? <hi>If they ſorrow after a godly ſort,</hi> as the <hi>Corinthians</hi> did for having ſided with that <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtuous Perſon,</hi> they will run through all the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> ſcale of Repentance. <hi>What carefulneſs will it work in them? what clearing of themſelves? what indignation? yea what fear? yea what vehement deſire? yea what zeal?</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:56821:16"/> 
               <hi>yea what revenge?</hi> If any <hi>Catiline</hi> hereafter ſhall dare to come into the <hi>Senate,</hi> they will preſently riſe from his Side, (as <hi>Caeſar</hi> and <hi>Craſſus</hi> did, though they both had abetted him formerly;) he will ſee himſelf de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted, and ready to be detected by thoſe that once encouraged him; Thus they may eaſily recover the falſe ſteps they have made by the Services they may do; and all this is little enough for their own and the Publick Security. For I muſt needs obſerve to you, that the King in my Text after he had offer'd Thanks to <hi>God for delivering him from the peril of the Sword,</hi> did not yet think himſelf ſo mighty ſafe, but that he had need to Pray in the very next words, <hi>Save me and deliver me from the hands of ſtrange Children!</hi> and what ſort of men were thoſe? his open Enemies? No, they were <hi>the ſtrange Children that diſſembled with him.</hi> For <hi>there are many that kiſs the hand which they would cut off,</hi> and we know by what Name he was call'd who <hi>Kiſt</hi> his Lord and Maſter even then when he led up the Band of men to ſeize him: it was <hi>the Traitor</hi> Judas; yet did not Chriſt reject his Addreſs, but gave him the title of <hi>Friend.</hi> But our Bleſſed Saviour himſelf has given out the ſureſt Teſt for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rended Converts, and he gave it to St. <hi>Peter</hi> upon foreſight that he would deny his Maſter, <hi>when thou art Converted ſtrengthen thy Brethren;</hi> ſuch Infant Converts as thoſe whoſe tender and weak Loyalty is now in danger of being over-laid and ſtifled by the preſſing importunity of the <hi>Party:</hi> They whoſe own Eyes are open'd ſhould endeavour to reduce thoſe whom
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:56821:16"/> their ill Example has been the cauſe of miſleading. But eſpecially they that have been guilty of <hi>Spiriting others away</hi> (for ſo it may well be called,) They ought to have dreadful apprehenſions of the <hi>Curſe upon thoſe that lead the Blind out of the way,</hi> unleſs they take care and pains to bring them home to their Duty. And now is the time, now that ſuch <hi>hidden works of darkneſs</hi> have been brought to light; that they muſt be <hi>blind</hi> indeed who will not ſee them: now that ſuch prodigies of Villany, have been diſcovered, that he is the greateſt prodigy of all that disbelieves, or denies them: Now that alſo ſo great a number, tho' I will not ſay <hi>the third Part of the Stars are ſmillen down</hi> (as they were in St. <hi>John</hi>'s Viſion) yet now that ſo many who ſhin'd heretofore in their proper Orbs are fallen: Now the Apoſtle will be allow'd to be in the Right, that <hi>Evil Communications corrupt good manners;</hi> and tho' it is now to be hop'd that noble minds will conſort with none hereafter as their <hi>Friends</hi> but with thoſe of their own temper; but tho' not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently as Friends, until they have reaſon to believe their <hi>Friendſhip</hi> on both ſides is founded upon Virtue, yet as <hi>Phyſicians,</hi> I muſt tell them from our Bleſſed Saviour, <hi>the whole need not the Phyſician, but thoſe that are ſick;</hi> then certainly thoſe that are <hi>poyſon'd</hi> have not only need but right to have an <hi>Antidote</hi> given' em by the ſame hand that hurt' em. And what a noble change, or rather what <hi>a glorious Transfiguration</hi> would be wrought upon theſe men, that were lately ſuch inſtruments of Miſchief; would they now turn <hi>Saviours</hi> in their kind, ſuch as
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:56821:17"/> the <hi>Prophet</hi> gives God thanks for, <hi>thou gaveſt them Saviours who ſaved them out of the hands of their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</hi> Nehem. ix. 27.</p>
            <p>And this I have ſaid to thoſe deluded men who I hope are coming to themſelves. But for the Atheiſts who make up one main ſtrength of the Party againſt us; I will not loſe my time in exhorting them to be Loyal, but rather employ it in imploring for them this only Charity of which they are capable, that they may be ſeverely puniſh'd and treated according to their merit. Let not ſuch wretched men be bolder <hi>in Blaſpheming God and the King,</hi> than we are in Aſſerting and Maintaining our Duty to them both. To what a height of this Virtue was <hi>David</hi> come, when he was able to ſay like one who had no longer any human thoughts about him, <hi>the Zeal of thy Houſe hath eaten me up,</hi> as a mighty flame devours whatever ſtand in its way: and it follows, <hi>the Rebukes of them that rebuked thee are fallen upon me.</hi> Again the ſame Royal Confeſſor, <hi>for thy ſake</hi> (ſays he) <hi>have I ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered reproof, ſhame hath covered my face,</hi> i. e. (ſays S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> upon that Pſalm) <hi>I was contented to be thought a ſhameleſs perſon, becauſe I would not be aſham'd of my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. Thou haſt need of this Confidence</hi> (ſays he) <hi>to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter ſome Peoples impudence; When they upbraid thee for being a worſhipper of one that was hanged upon a Tree, if thou doſt bluſh for ſhame thou art Guilty</hi> (ſays he) <hi>of a grievous Sin—</hi>Quid fronti times quam ſigno crucis ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſti—prorſus eſto frontoſus. (i. e.) <hi>Remember that thou wert arm'd in thy forehead with the ſign of the Croſs,</hi> (ſo long ago it was uſed) <hi>therefore be not weak-foreheaded</hi> (ſays he) <hi>in the Cauſe of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:56821:17"/>
            <p> As Heroick an example of ſuch a pious magnanimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty as this in <hi>David,</hi> was that in King <hi>Lewis</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> I mean him whom they ſtile <hi>the Saint,</hi> and well they may ſtile him ſo upon this account; that having made an <hi>Edict</hi> againſt Atheiſtical or prophane talking, with this Penalty annex'd, that the Guilty Perſon ſhould be <hi>Branded in the Forehead</hi> with a hot Iron, when great Interceſſion was us'd to procure a Pardon for a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Right Honorable Offender, the King comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that Execution ſhould be done immediately, and added this memorable ſaying, <hi>That he would gladly t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e the Brand in his own Forehead, on condition the name of God ſhould no more be blaſphemed in his Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But having done with our Enemies, before I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, there is ſomewhat to be ſaid to our Friends, to our ſelves: <hi>If we ſing a new Song unto God</hi> for this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance, <hi>If we ſing praiſes unto him,</hi> then the Son of <hi>Syrach</hi> will tell us, <hi>that praiſe is not comely in the mouth of a ſinner, for it was not ſent him of the Lord.</hi> If therefore <hi>we will ſing a new Song of Praiſe to God</hi> as we ought to do, then we muſt lead <hi>new lives</hi> too: we muſt conſider that the moſt deceitful enemy of <hi>all</hi> is <hi>within, Intus ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtis, intus periculum,</hi> and the greateſt victory that we have to gain in this world, is over our ſelves, and within our ſelves; a <hi>victory</hi> over our own unruly paſſions within us; <hi>For he that is ſlow to anger is better than the mighty, and he that ruleth his ſpirit than he that taketh a City,</hi> Prov. 16. 32. and a <hi>victory</hi> over the many Temptations from without, conſpiring with the Tempters within us; <hi>For he that reſiſteth pleaſures</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:56821:18"/> 
               <hi>crowneth his life, Ecclus.</hi> 19. 5. This were indeed a glorious victory: 'tis properly that which the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle</hi> calls <hi>overcoming the world:</hi> and if <hi>Alexander</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd to be ſtil'd <hi>the Great</hi> for Conquering but ſome parts of it, when yet his wild Appetites had the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion over him; then let but theſe be ſubdu'd, and we juſtly triumph.</p>
            <p>Such a deliverance from our Luſts, would be a mercy tranſcendently greater than even this by which God has given us our lives; for that would ſave our ſouls too. The greateſt courage in the world may find room enough to exerciſe and ſhew it ſelf in a thorough Penitent; as 'tis excellently argued by S. <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> That <hi>David</hi> ſhew'd a more undaunted greatneſs of mind in daring to think of ſurmounting the ſin, and the ſhame, and to ſet up again for a Saint, after his foul, Treacherous, and Bloody Offence <hi>in the matter of Uriah,</hi> than he had ſhewn' in his ſingle Combat with <hi>Goliah</hi> of <hi>Gath.</hi> But a Victory that <hi>gives not God this glory,</hi> a Victory that leaves it to be ſaid of us, <hi>they repented not to give him Glory,</hi> ſuch a Victory <hi>may</hi> be more perillous than even <hi>the Sword it ſelf</hi> from which we are deliver'd. Good Fortune, unleſs we uſe it reverently, joyning good Minds to good For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, <hi>may</hi> be one of the dangerouſeſt things that can happen to us: But as to mend our lives would be to make the beſt uſe of our preſent advantage; as to forſake our ſins would be the braveſt conqueſt over ourſelves: ſo it would be the heighth of Gratitude for our Deliverance. The <hi>Heathens</hi> on ſuch an occaſion
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:56821:18"/> as this would have built a <hi>Temple to Jupiter</hi> the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervatory</hi> But this would be done like Chriſtians in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, to dedicate our ſelves as <hi>Temples of the Holy Ghoſt, to God the Preſerver of men,</hi> as the <hi>Prophet</hi> ſtiles him.</p>
            <p>Let this great work be done, and then we may conclude with the <hi>Pſalm,</hi> and ſecure our ſelves of all the Temporal Bleſſings here annex'd to ſincere Piety, <hi>That our Sons ſhall grow up as the young plants, That our Garners ſhall be full and plenteous with all manner of ſtore, That our ſheep ſhall bring forth thouſands and ten thou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſands, that ſo there may be no decay, no leading into captivity, nor no complaining in our ſtreets; Happy are the people that are in ſuch a caſe; yea, Bleſſed are the People who have the Lord for their God:</hi> which God we ought All to Adore, Invoke, and moſt humbly Beſeech that the Church, which it was his good Providence ſo to Reform, as to make it the Beſt, the Pureſt, the moſt Apoſtolical of any Church upon Earth; This he would vouchſafe to Preſerve (now that all her Enemies are vanquiſht by dint of Argument) from <hi>Periſhing by the Sword</hi> in the Perſon of Her Gracious Sovereign, ſince ſhe never <hi>takes the Sword</hi> againſt Her Lawful Sovereign. To which good Prayer let me but add thoſe Petitions which a moſt ancient Writer tells us the Primitive Chriſtians us'd to make for their Emperor; <hi>For his long Life, for the Peace of his Empire, for the ſafety of the Royal Family, for Valiant Soldiers under him, for a Faithful Senate, an Honeſt Commonalty, a Quiet World,</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:56821:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>and whatſoever elſe ought to be the ſubject of our Prayers, as He is a man whom we pray for, or as He is</hi> Caeſar.</p>
            <p>And we may the better hope that God will accept theſe Prayers we make for the KING, becauſe the King himſelf is here in Devotion with us to ſay <hi>AMEN.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:56821:19"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
